اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
The Muslims assembled their army of 40 to 45,000 soldiers
while, their opponent was about 250,000.
And Heraclius has chosen the battlefield, by sending a letter to his brother Theodore, who was the head of his armies.
He said: Choose a place that offers a lot of space for fighting, but very narrow for retreat.
Because he wanted to force his soldiers into fighting,
they've already experienced fighting the Muslims, in a few incidents before.
You have the Battle of Mu'ta(مؤته) and then Ajnadeen(أجنادين) that just happened before Al-Yarmook(يرموك).
The one, we talked about last time.
In which Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) went to rescue Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) in Falastine(فلسطين)
and they routed the Roman army and it was disastrous defeat for the Roman emperor.
So now he assembled a huge army and he told his brother, Theodore,
to make sure that there's no place to retreat.
So we can force our soldiers to fight.
So in addition to them, having their backs towards the cliff, overlooking the valley of Al-Yarmook(أليرموك),
they also had the infantry, the soldiers, every 10 were tied to each other in chains.
So every group of 10 soldiers had a chain, binding them together,
so that if somebody wants to run away, he has to convince the whole group.
Plus it makes it very difficult for them to move, therefore, it's almost a fixed position.
Not all of the infantry were like that, but such a huge number of them were chained.
And that was, I mean, not the first time this method was employed,
because in the Battle of Dat-As-Salasal(ذات ألسلاسل), the same thing happened with Amr Bin Al-Aas رضي الله عنه,
so this was a method employed actually to force these soldiers to fight.
So now, it was Romans who chose this battlefield
and when Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص), he saw that he said to the Muslims;
أبشروا وقلما جاء محصور بخير
Rejoice for the good news because rarely does a person, who's cornered, win.
They are the ones, who chose to corner themselves into this position.
So this is the beginning of the good news, that's a good omen for us.
The Roman army was divided into squadrons that was their method in fighting.
While it wasn't a tradition in Arabia to use that method,
but the first time it was used was in Al-Yarmook(يرموك).
And it was the suggestion of Khalid Ibn Walid رضي الله عنه to use it.
So, he divided the army into squadrons, each squad was made up of 1000 soldiers,
so he had between 40 to 45 squadrons in the army,
and he would appoint a leader over each of these groups.
The heart or the center was made up of about 18 squadrons, so we're talking about 18,000
and was headed by Abu Obaidah Amr Bin Jarrah(أبوعبيدةعمروبن جرَّاح).
The right flank 10 squadrons we're talking about 10,000
and this was headed by Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص)
and Sharhabil Bin Hasana(شرحبيل بن حسنة) was assisting him.
And the left flank 10 squadrons and it was headed by Yazeed Ibn Abi Sufiyan(يزيدإبن أبي سفيان).
In the front Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) placed a very small group of cavalry
that could be very fast in maneuvering and would not be very restricted in their movement.
He placed them in the front and then in the rear,
he placed 5000 soldiers under the leadership of Saeed Bin Zaid(سعيد بن زيد).
And the role of this group of 5000 was to defend
and take care of the Muslim families and their property.
See with all of these Mujahideen(مجاهدين) they came in with their families
and their wealth, their property, everything, Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
And you can't just leave them somewhere without protection.
So they had to accompany the army in order to be close to the protection.
So it was a very risky business don't think that for the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم
and the ones, who joined them, it was an easy thing.
I mean, you just enlist in the army and go and fight for six months and then you're back, it was such a sacrifice.
Now not all of them would take their families with them,
but the ones who came from very distance and faraway lands,
they will bring in their families and they will just settle in that land.
And many of these fighters when Ash-Sham(ألشَّام) was opened,
they did not go back to their original lands, they stayed there.
And they inhabited those areas and they spread on the religion and they made Da'wah(دعوة),
so their whole life was given to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, it was fighting and Da'wah(دعوة).
Ad-Da'wah Wal-Jihad(ألدعوة والجهاد), that's how they lived.
So this was the formation of the Muslim army
and Abu Dardah رضي الله عنه was appointed Qazi(قاضي), the judge for the army,
if you get into disputes and problems.
So the army has to have a judge, and that was a Abu Dardah(أبودرداء).
Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود), he was the paymaster,
he was dealing with the finances of the army.
Al-Miqdad Bin Amr Bin Aswad(ألمقداد إبن عمرو بن أسود), he was the Qari(قاري) for the army.
This was something started by Rasool Allah ﷺ in the Battle of Badr(بدر).
Rasool Allah ﷺ appointed Al-Miqdad(ألمقداد)
to go around the army reciting the Surah(سورة) of Jihad(جهاد), which is Al-Anfal(ألأنفال).
So he would go around reciting the Ayaat(آيات) from Surat-Ul-Anfaal(سورة الأنفال) to the army.
And this tradition was carried on and was employed in the Battle of Yarmook(يرموك)
and Khalid(خالد) appointed the same person to do it,
Miqdad Ibn Aswad(ألمقداد إبن أسود), who did it in the Battle of Badr(بدر) with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And then there was the motivator for the army, Al-Waiz(ألوائظ).
The one who would go around, encouraging the soldiers because Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) is gonna come to you.
And he's gonna remind you about your family
and he's gonna remind you about your wealth
and he's gonna throw all of this Waswasah(وسوسة) in your heart.
So there needs to be somebody who's going to give you Naseeha(نَصيحة).
See in Surat-Ul-Asr(سورة العصر) Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ tells us the solution
to the state of lost that every man is in.
وَالْعَصْرِ ۝ إِنَّ الْإِنْسَانَ لَفِي خُسْرٍ۝
In the name of time! Man is in a state of loss,
إِلَّا الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا وَعَمِلُوا الصَّالِحَاتِ ۝ وَتَوَاصَوْا بِالْحَقِّ وَتَوَاصَوْا بِالصَّبْرِ۝
Except for those, who believe,
آمَنُوا وَعَمِلُوا الصَّالِحَاتِ۝
They do good,
وَتَوَاصَوْا بِالْحَقِّ وَتَوَاصَوْا بِالصَّبْرِ۝
And they support and advise each other in Haqq(حَقّ) and Sabr(صبر), in the truth,
they advise each other to follow Al-Haqq(ألحَقّ), which is Islam, the truth
and Sabr(صبر), they encourage each other to be patient.
So when you see me weak, you uplift me.
And when I see you weak, I would do the same. This is the,
وَتَوَاصَوْا بِالصَّبْرِ۝
They would encourage each other to be patient,
the one who would do that for the army was Abu Sufiyan Ibn Harb(أبوسفيان إبن حرب).
And this is the power of Islam.
Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان), who was the leader of the effort to fight Muhammadﷺ,
all the way until close to the death of Muhammadﷺ
he turns around and he himself becomes a Muslim.
Not only does he become a Muslim, but a very enthusiastic one.
Turns around and now the one, who was motivating
and mobilizing all of the tribes to fight Muhammadﷺ
he is now the one encouraging them to fight the enemies of Muhammadﷺ.
So Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان), he would go and speak to each Squadron and give them Mu'aza(مؤعظة).
And he would then go to the women and give them Mu'aza(مؤعظة) too
because the women had a very important role to play.
They were not just sitting in the tents, to be defended by the men
the women were responsible for the services of the Army,
in addition to their role in fighting too.
And in the Battle of Yarmook(يرموك),
the women did participate in fighting and we'll get to that and the reason, why they had to fight.
And the general commander is Khalid Ibn Walid رضي الله عنه.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) invented this or employed this method of dividing the army into squadrons
because it's a large army.
So far the Muslims have never had an army that's 40,000 strong.
It was much smaller numbers, therefore, you didn't need to split the army in this way.
In the Battle of Badr(بدر) it was 300, a little over 300.
They didn't have to be split.
Rasool Allah ﷺ the formation that he used was center, right and left that's it.
And this carried on and in many of the battles because of their method of fighting,
which is the raiding method of attacking and then retreating,
you can't have that strict formation.
But now since it's a large army, it has to be more organized.
So he divided it into these squadrons.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), he told the army, he gave them a Khut'ba(خطبة), a speech and he said;
هذا يومٌ من أيَّام الله
This is a day from amongst the days of Allah.
See, everyday belongs to Allah but when he says this is the day of the days of Allah,
he means that this is a special day.
These battles were decisive moments in history.
Many of them only took one day.
The Battle of Badr(بدر) was one day, Uhud(أحَد) was one day.
Fathh-Makkah(فتح مكَّه) was one day.
But these were life changing events for the Muslim community and they change the coarse of history.
So Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), before the battle,
he is telling them, this is a day of the days of Allah.
There should be in it neither pride nor wrongdoing, throw away all of the pride
because now Khalid(خالد) is dealing with different people, from different backgrounds, from different tribes.
So there's a lot of room for competition and pride and showing off who's stronger.
So Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) is saying: Throw all of that away, leave it behind you.
And it's not the day of wrongdoing.
Every day we're supposed to stay away from sins, but this is a special day.
So there's an added emphasis; be careful, on this day be closer to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ than usual.
Make your striving sincere, Ikhlaas(إخلاص),
he is giving them the Naseeha(نَصيحة) of Ikhlaas(إخلاص),
which is very important in every Ibadah(عبادة), especially in their Ibadah(عبادة) of Jihad(جهاد)
because you might die the next moment.
So you have to have Ikhlaas(إخلاص).
Seeking Allah by your work for this day also has what lies beyond it.
And then Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) would go around encouraging the army.
Bahaan(بحان), one of the leaders of the Romans.
He wanted to meet with Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), so he came ahead
and he asked for Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) to come and meet him.
So they met each other.
Bahaan(بحان) said: We heard that you came out in search of booty
because you are very hungry and destitute people.
So I'm offering you 10 Dinar(دينار) each for every soldier in addition to a set of clothes, and food
and next year, we'll give you the same.
Now, first of all, that was the reputation of the tribes of Arabia,
that their life is based on raiding others.
Number two, many people cannot understand the motivation behind Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
They don't comprehend it and until this day, they don't understand it.
They fail to see that, it is for the sake of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ
a person who's dying is dying for the sake of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ for something greater, for Jannah(جنة), to please Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Somebody whose thinking is limited to this world,
and cannot go beyond that doesn't understand this concept.
Why are you throwing yourself in this danger, why are you killing yourself?
How came you are doing that?
So he's saying that if you're here for money, I'm going to give you money.
Go back to your land!
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) and Allah Alam(الله أعلم),
how come Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) responded in this way?
Maybe he felt because the man is being, sarcastic
I don't want to say sarcastic but maybe he's belittling the Muslims by such a statement.
But Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), he said: No, that's not why we came.
We came because we are people, who drink blood!
And we heard that the best tasting blood is the blood of the Romans.
So obviously, that's not an answer that Bahaan(بحان) liked.
Bahaan(بحان) said: Well, we heard that about you.
Not in that sense, but in the sense that you are very ruthless people.
And that was the reputation of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد).
See Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), a legend was developing around them.
Some of it is true, and some of it is false.
Because later on when the battle started,
a man who's mentioned in At-Tabari(ألطبري) as Gerja(جرجه), which most likely he is George.
You know, an Arabic sometimes the non Arabic names,
when they're converted to Arabic would sound very different.
So he tried to find what is the closest Latin name to it, because these were Latin names.
So most likely Gerja(جرجه) would be George.
He was one of the Roman generals.
During the fighting, he came to Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
and he said: I want to meet you, so they met. Gerja(جرجه) said;
I'm gonna ask you in the name of God, and I want you to tell me the truth and don't lie to me.
Because a free man doesn't lie.
They had this chivalry and he is saying to Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد): You are free, man. I'm a free man.
You have to be honest with me, I'll be honest with you.
So he said: I want you to tell me the truth.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) said: I will tell you the truth.
He said: Is it true that your prophet has received a sword from God, and then he gave it to you.
Therefore you never lose in any battle?
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) he could have said: Yes…
And built upon that reputation that already existed
and carry the legend further and promoted it.
But he didn't. He said: No, that's not true.
What happened is Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has sent us a prophet, who invited us to the truth.
Some of us believed in him, while some of us fought against him.
I was amongst those who fought against him.
Until Allah سبحانه وتعالى took us by our hearts, gripped our hearts,
and brought us forth to Islam, so I became a Muslim.
So, Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), in other words, is saying that we were his enemies,
but then Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ gripped our hearts and brought us to Islam.
It was something from the heart we aren't forced into it.
Muhammadﷺ did not force it down on our throats.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ brought our hearts to Him.
Amr Bin Al-Aas رضي الله عنه before he died, he said;
There was a time when the most disliked person to me, was Muhammadﷺ
and at that time, my greatest desire would be to lay my hands on him and kill him if I could.
But then Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ put the love of Islam in my heart
so Muhammadﷺ became the most beloved to me.
And he said: I used to love him so much and have so much respect to him.
I couldn't even look him straight in the eye, I would lower my gaze whenever I see him.
So, Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) said: Allah gripped our hearts and we became Muslim.
And then Muhammadﷺ told me;
أنت سيفٌ مِنْ سُيوفِ اللهِ،  سَلَّهُ اللهُ على المشركين
He told me you are a sword among the swords of Allah.
And Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has drawn you out against the disbelievers.
Thus, I was named the sword of Allah according to that for I am the harshest of the Muslims against the polytheists.
I am the harshest of the Muslims among Al-Mushrikeen(ألمشركين).
So that harshness of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) and his skill and his ability
and his intelligence, his speed, his willingness to take risk,
is what made Khalid Ibn Walid رضي الله عنه, the man he was.
When I talked about the adventure of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) to make Hajj(حَجْ)
and then his decision to cross the desert
that no one else has crossed before, uncharted territory
that shows you a nature that the majority of the Muslims today have lost.
Muslims have become very timid, they're unwilling to change their ways, the wrong ways.
And they're sort of fixed into a certain course and a certain way of living,
and there's no willingness to improve.
And it seems that even the type of work that we're involved in has an effect on our personality.
Definitely work does have an effect on the personality,
but the particular line of work of being an employee,
where you just do work and then at the end of the month, you receive the fixed salary,
and there's no risk involved that makes a person fear.
So, this I might call it enterprising, or entrepreneurship ability that Sahabah رضي الله عنهم had
allowed them to become who they were, by the Taufeeq(توفيق) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
See, I want to make sure that whenever I talk about the skill of one of a Sahabah رضي الله عنهم
we don't attribute their success to that because at the end, it is the Taufeeq(توفيق) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
See, as a Muslim, you cannot succeed in anything without the Taufeeq(توفيق) of Allah,
the Taufeeq(توفيق) of Allah is the willingness of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ and His guidance for you.
So we are not attributing anything to their skills,
and that is not something we are supposed to do because with Qaroon(قارون),
Qaroon(قارون) and he did not thank Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ for the wealth that Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has given him.
When he was asked how did you make you wealthy, he said;
إِنَّمَا أُوتِيتُهُۥ عَلَىٰ عِلْمٍ عِندِى ۚ
I made my fortune because of my skills.
He didn't say because Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ gave it to me.
So that's being ungrateful. That is Jaht-In-Neimah(جهت انعمة).
That's rejecting the blessing of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
So we attribute everything to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, we say Al-Hamdulillah(ألحمدلله)
Praise be to Allah for what he has abled us to do.
But we have to improve ourselves and we have to put the effort in it
and ask Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ to help us and when we do improve,
we say Al-Hamdulillah(ألحمدلله) for allowing us to be like we are.
So the Muslims need to change their lifestyle
and the way they view the future Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ is going to provide you with the Rizq(رزق).
It's going to come from Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ
for many they live a life of slavery.
You work for the whole month make a salary, work for the next month.
No Da'wah(دعوة), no Islamic work, nothing.
Why?
Because I have to make a living, I have to make a salary, it's a slavery.
Just like a slave, who's working day and night to make a living
and has no plans for the future, whatsoever has no vision of what life is going to be?
And that's why when Islam freed the slaves, it did it, in a way
where they first would psychologically change before they actually get their physical freedom.
Because if you just give a slave freedom immediately because of the long life in slavery,
there is a lot of psychological damage that is done to such a person.
So sometimes they do not succeed, in a life of freedom.
So Islam has first of all broken these restrictive rules of slavery.
So you'd have scholars like Atta'a(عطاء), who was a former slave,
Bilal Ibn Rabah رضي الله عنه was a former slave,
Salman Al-Farsi(سلمان ألفارسي) was former slave.
Islam change their psychology first and then after that they got their freedom.
So by the time they were free, they were able to lead the free life.
So this man George, he asked Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
he told him; What does your religion teach you?
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) said, that we invite you to Islam.
He said: And what if we don’t.
He said: Then you must pay Jizya(جزية).
He said: What if we don't? He said: Then we fight you.
So Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) is telling him, the three levels.
Number one, invitation to Islam! If you accept it, then you become one of us.
If not, then the next step is paying Al-Jizya(جزية).
If you refuse that then it is Qital(قتال), fighting.
So George asked Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), he said:
And if somebody becomes Muslim, what's their status among you?
He said: You become one of us, equal to us.
Gerja(جرجه) said: So there is no seniority, if a person becomes a late comer into the religion,
they're equal to the ones, who have been Muslim before.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) said: And you become better.
He said: How can that be?
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) said: Because we have seen the miracles of Muhammadﷺ,
we have witnessed them with our own eyes, so it was obvious.
But for you, you have not met Muhammadﷺ,
you've not seen him and he did not see his miracles.
Nevertheless, you become a Muslim that gives you a higher status.
So George said: What does one have to do, if he wants to become a Muslim? He said: You say,
أَشْهَدُ أَنْ لَا إِلَهَ إِلَّا اللَّهُ وَأَشْهَدُ أَنَّ مُحَمَّدًا رَسُول الله
He repeated those words, and he turned around, and he fought on side, the Muslims,
and he died in that battle as a Shaheed(شَهِيد).
And that's why the Scholars say that Shahadah(شَهَادَة) is the one deed in Islam that doesn't need any deed before it.
A Shaheed(شَهِيد) doesn't have to do anything before that,
Shahadah(شَهَادَة) is enough to grant them a high level in Jannah(جنة)
without them doing anything before it,
no Salah(صلاة), no Sayam(صيام), no Zakah(زكوة) nothing, no Zikr(زكر),
أَشْهَدُ أَنْ لَا إِلَهَ إِلَّا اللَّهُ وَأَشْهَدُ أَنَّ مُحَمَّدًا رَسُول الله
And Shahadah(شَهَادَة) that's it, you got the higher level in Jannah(جنة).
So the battle started, Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) told the right and left flanks to move ahead.
They charged, now the Romans in terms of numbers were overwhelming the Muslims.
So in the beginning, when the right and left flank of the Muslim army attacked,
and the Romans responded back, the multitude of numbers that were coming forth
against the Muslim army was so much for them to bear.
So the right and left flank ended up retreating.
They retreated so far, that the Roman soldiers were able to reach close to the camp grounds for the Muslim women.
And that is when the women had to join and fight, because now the army is right there.
So the retreat was so bad it pushed the Muslim army so far behind
that they reached to the fixed basis of the Muslim army.
So the women came out and fought.
Javeria(جويرية), the daughter of Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) was fighting.
Umm Hakim(أم حكيم) was fighting
the daughter of Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) was running to the men
and telling them shame on you, you're gonna run and leave us.
So the women played a dual role.
One of them is actually to fight and it says in At-Tabari(ألطبري), they carried their swords and they fought.
And the other role was to throw rocks at these Muslim soldiers, who are running away
and call them to go back and fight.
So that was the role that the Muslim women played in the Battle of Al-Yarmook(يرموك).
Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذإبن جبل), he was encouraging the ones around him.
Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) was going around one of the Sahabah(صحابه) said;
There was a calmness during the fight.
There was a calmness in voice during the fight, and then I suddenly heard somebody say;
يَا نصرالله أقترب ، يَا نصرالله أقترب
O victory of Allah come close, O victory of Allah come close.
So I wanted to know who that loud voice belonged to.
And I went and found Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) going around his son
and encouraging everyone and making Dua(دُعَا) to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
So that was how enthusiastic Abu Sufiyan رضي الله عنه was in Ghazwa Tul-Yarmook(غزوة اليرموك).
So things were improving a little bit,
and the Muslims were succeeding and pushing them further away.
So they pushed them back to their original locations, and even further back.
So now the tables were turning.
Khalid Ibn Walid رضي الله عنه heading a group of Horsemen of about 100
which was very swift and maneuverable.
He decided to make an attack on the left flank of the Roman army.
Allah Ho Alam(الله أعلم) why he particularly chose that part of the army to attack
maybe it was because of the location.
So he made an attack and it was such a strong blow to the army.
6000 Roman fighters died in that single attack.
So it was such a very strong blow to the left flank of the Army,
and then Khalid(خالد) withdraw back and he told his men, he said:
In the Name of Allah, they have no patience and strength more than what you have seen.
In other words, we have pushed them to the limit, they can't do any better.
Which means we just need to press a little further, until we push them to the breaking point.
So Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) attacking again
and encouraging the Muslims of the right flank under Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) to push.
And they succeeded in Tatweek(تطويق), in besieging the Roman army,
so just imagine 45,000, besieging 250,000.
So they succeeded in besieging them now, because Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) said,
that's the end of it, they cannot fight, they're reaching the breaking point
and Allah Alam(ألله أعلم) how Khalid Ibn Walid رضي الله عنه made that judgment.?
Maybe it's by the response that he's seeing from them or the looks on their faces.
He said: Just attack them and surround them.
So they rounded the army from three sides and their back was towards the trench.
Now obviously, there's such a huge army to besiege.
So what Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) then did,
He commanded his men to drive a wedge between the cavalry and the infantry, of the Roman army.
So they succeeded in doing that.
So now the cavalry is separated from the infantry.
The horsemen are separate from the foot soldiers.
And then Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) gave his command to Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص),
he told him open an exit door for the cavalry.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) knew that their will, to fight is over,
and now they just want to survive.
He knew that they have been pushed to the limit, and that's the end of the resistance.
So he told Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) to open up because now they're surrounded from each side.
He told him: Open up, give them a way out,
and as soon as Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) did that, the cavalry just ran out.
And they went into the desert, each one is trying to survive.
So now you have the foot soldiers without any cover.
And that is when the Muslim army just started pushing them further and further and further.
Now At-Tabari(ألطبري) says that as soon as two men out of the 10 were knocked away, were killed and knocked off the cliff.
They would drag the entire group.
He said that 80,000 Roman soldiers plunged into the cliff, 80,000.
The total number of losses among the Roman army totaled around 120,000 Soldiers.
80,000 of them in the cliff, they were just falling in numbers, because by now it was nighttime.
And the soldiers are just running away and they don't know what which direction to take.
So some of them are just jumping off the cliff.
Plus, these men, who were chained up their chains ended up killing them.
And that was the prophecy of Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص), he said;
وقلما ياتي بمحصور بخير
These people have cornered themselves, a cliff and chains, that's all what you need.
And Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) spent his night in the pavilion of Theodore.
Theodore himself was killed.
So now Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) is staying in the tents of the Roman General and the fight is going on at night.
They're just finishing off these soldiers, the ones who are left behind and couldn't run away.
So it was a great victory for the Muslim and that's why
the day of Al-Yarmook(يرموك) is such a memorable event in the history of Islam.
Not only because of what happened during the day of Al-Yarmook(يرموك),
but because Al-Yarmook(يرموك) was actually the turning point in the Fatoohaat(فتوحات) of Ash-Sham(ألشَّام)
because of what happened during Al-Yarmook(يرموك)
the resistance of the Roman Empire in Ash-Sham(ألشَّام) was broken.
And after that, it was just one city falling after another.
And Ash-Sham(ألشَّام) was the gateway to Africa and to Europe.
That is how the Muslims opened Egypt and then North Africa.
So it was a very, very important event.
3000 Muslims died, among them were many Sahabah(صحابه),
one of them was Ikrimah Bin Abi Jahal(عكرمة بن أبي جهل).
And the situation of Ikrimah(عكرمة) is fascinating
because Ikrimah(عكرمة) first of all, he's the son of Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل)
the worst enemy of Rasool Allah ﷺ, the Firaun(فرعون) of this Ummah(امة), he is pharaoh of this Ummah(امة).
Number two Ikrimah(عكرمة) himself was not different than his father.
Ikrimah(عكرمة) was the second most important figure
after Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد).
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) at that time was fighting against the Muslims.
It was Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) and Ikrimah(عكرمة),
who routed the Muslims and caused the defeat of the Muslims in the battle of Uhud(أحَد).
Ikrimah Bin Abi Jahal(عكرمة بن أبي جهل) was one of the worst enemies of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
until Fath-E-Makkah(فتح مكه).
On the day of Yarmook(يرموك), look at what Ikrimah(عكرمة) did?
Ikrimah(عكرمة) said: I have fought against Rasool Allah ﷺ, so many times,
now on this day shall I retreat.
I have fought against Muhammadﷺ so many times I need to make up for that.
So on this day when Allah is giving me a chance, shall I retreat.
So to ensure that he's going to fight until the last moment,
he called upon his close associates and he was ahead of a squadron.
He called upon his close associates, among them, his uncle Al-Haris Bin Hishaam(ألحارث بن هشام),
and Ziraar Ibn Azwar(ضرار إبن أزور),
and many of the others Sahabah(صحابه) and he said:
Let's give each other a pledge to die Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
In other words, we're gonna throw ourselves plunge into the army of the enemy.
And since we made an oath not to live, we need to stay there until we get Shahadah(شَهَادَة)
that's pretty much the Baiyah(بَيْعة) that they gave.
ألبيعة ألموت، تبابعنا على الموت
We pledge allegiance to die, we're not going to come back alive.
And this is by the way, one of the evidences, scholars use for the validity of martyrdom operations
Amaliyatil Istashhadiyyah(عملية الأستشهادية).
That these Sahabah(صحابه) but not all of them are Sahabah(صحابه) obviously.
Ikrimah(عكرمة) was a Sahabi(صحابي), Al-Haris Bin Hishaam(ألحارث بن هشام) was a Sahabi(صحابي),
Ziraar Ibn Azwar(ضرار إبن أزور) was Sahabi(صحابي), the total number of the group was 400, by the way,
this was not a small group 400, they pledged to die.
Why is it used by the scholars as an evidence to support Al-Amaliyatil Istash'hadiyyah(عملية الأستشهادية),
it is because of the fact that they promised to die
and to do their best to get Shahadah(شَهَادَة).
The entire group 400, we're laying down on the battleground, so they fulfilled their oath.
Some of them were actually killed and the others were injured so severely that they couldn't move any further.
So they have fulfilled the oath, they did their best.
So the ones, who survived didn't survive because they broke the oath.
They survived because their injuries were so bad, it incapacitated, they couldn't move anymore.
Now, you must have heard about the story of the Sahabah(صحابه), who were dying and then they offered them water.
So each one of them would turn down the offer and say give it to the one next to me.
You heard that story, right?
That actually happened within this group, in Battle of Al-Yarmook(يرموك).
They gave one of them water. So he said: Give it to my brother, he needs it more than I do.
So the water would go to that person, he would say give it to my other brother
who needs this more than I do.
So the water would make a full circle and come back to the same person,
whom it was offered to before, but by the time most of them are already dead.
So this is an example of no fear, willingness to die for the sake of Allah and Eesaar(إيثار)
sacrifice for your brother, he needs the water more than I do.
It was a great victory for the Muslims, but the tone of celebration was subdued.
Because the news of the death of the Khalifah(خليفه) was announced.
According to the story of At-Tabari(ألطبري) before the battle started,
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) receives a messenger from Madina.
The messenger gives Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) a letter
stating that Al-Khalifah(ألخليفه) Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) has passed away
and the new Khalifah(خليفه) is Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
And that Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) is giving Abu Obaidah Amr Bin Jarrah(أبوعبيدةعمروبن جرَّاح) the command of the Muslim army.
So Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) was moved from his post
and was replaced by Abu Obaidah Amr Bin Jarrah(أبوعبيدةعمروبن جرَّاح).
According to At-Tabari(ألطبري) Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) concealed this letter,
and told the messenger not to speak to anyone, and he actually held him,
with him in his tent, to make sure that he's not going to leak out the news.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) made the judgment that if the news of the death of Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق)
reaches to the soldiers in this critical moment, it's not the good timing.
Now, they need to be thinking about what's facing them.
The battle did not start yet, so I don't want to distract them with such catastrophic news
the death of the Khalifah(خليفه) Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
So he decided to hide the news, until the battle was over, and the victory was achieved.
And then he announced the news to the Muslims, and he stepped down
and he handed leadership of the armies in Ash-Sham(ألشَّام) to Abu Obaidah(أبوعبيدة).
And that was basically the last time Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) assumes a position of leadership.
Because Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه has made the decision that
Khalid Ibn Walid رضي الله عنه, his sword is too sharp
and it's time to change him with someone else.
Now Ibn Taymiyah(اِبْنِ تَيْمِيَّه) as I mentioned to you before, he said that,
The reasoning is that and the wisdom behind that, is that if the Khalifah(خليفه) is very strict,
he has to have somebody under him, who's soft,
and if the Khalifah(خليفه) is soft, then he has to have somebody under him who's very strict.
So Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق), and Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) go together very well.
One is lenient, and the other one is strict,
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) and Abu Obaidah(أبوعبيدة) go together very well
because Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) is very strict and Abu Obaidah(أبوعبيدة) is very soft and compassionate.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه he bathed in a day that was very cold,
so he catched a fever.
And his fever was developing day by day so in this situation was getting worse, every day.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه felt that this is the end of his life.
His life is coming to a closing.
So now the concern of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه is who to appoint as my successor.
So he's making Shura(شورى), he invites Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف),
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf رضي الله عنه comes in, Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) asks him,
What do you say about Umar(عُمَر)?
What's your view about Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)?
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) said: Anything that you asked me, you have better knowledge of.
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) is saying that you are the most knowledgeable among us, about everything.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said: I want to hear your opinion.
Abdur Rahman  Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) said;
My view is that Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) is better than what you think.
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) knew why, Abu Bakr(أبوبكر) was asking him this question.
He knew that he's asking him to determine,
who was the best fit person for the position of Khilafah(خِلَافَه).
So Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) is saying
that he is even better than what do you think.
In other words, he's right person.
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف), by the way, could be one of the contenders for the position.
He is one of the Ashra Mubashireen Bil Jannah(عَشرةمبشرين بالجنَّة).
Now obviously, the post of the Khilafah(خِلَافَه) is not going to go to anyone outside of the 10
if there's someone among the 10, who's living.
These 10 according to the consensus of the Sahabah(صحابه) are the greatest and these 10 are
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), Umar(عُمَر), Uthman(عثمان), Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب),
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف), Talha Bin Obaidellah(طلحةبن عبيدالله),
Az-Zubair Bin Awwam(ألزبير بن عوام), Abu Obaidah Amr Bin Jarrah(أبوعبيدةعمروبن جرَّاح),
Saeed Bin Zaid Bin Nufail(سعيدبن زيد بن نفيل) and Sa'ad Ibn Abi Waqas(سعدإبن أبي وقاص),
these are the 10.
So, Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن) is one of them.
So he's saying that he is better than what you think.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said;
Then conceal this matter, and don't tell anyone about it, this conversation.
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) said: Of course! And then he left.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه invited Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان),
so Uthman(عثمان) came, Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said;
What is your view on Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه.?
Uthman Ibn Affan رضي الله عنه said: In the Name of Allah,
I believe that what Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) does in private
is better than what he does openly.
Meaning what we see of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
and the greatness of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب),
the outside of him, what he does in private, when nobody can see him is even better.
And then he said;
وليس فينا مِثلَ
And there is none among us like him.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه told Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان), he told him:
If I would bypass, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) it's not going to get beyond you.
If I decide not to appoint Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب),
you are going to be the person in that post.
And then he invited Usaid Bin Khuzair(أسيدبن خضير) and he sought his opinion on that.
And Usaid Bin Khuzair(أسيدبن خضير) said;
اللهمَّ أعْلم ألخير بعدك
I think that he's the best after you.
He is happy with what makes the Muslims pleased.
He is pleased with what pleases the Muslims, and he dislikes what the Muslims dislike,
meaning he is the man for the Ummah(امة), he cares for the Ummah(امة).
His concern is for the Ummah(امة), if something pleases the Ummah(امة), it pleases him.
If something harms the Ummah(امة), he dislikes that.
He is not a person, who will look for his own benefit to the detriment of the Ummah(امة).
He is a person, who will live for us.
Everyone Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه consults would give him the same answer,
similar answers, with the exception of Talha Bin Obaidellah(طلحةبن عبيدالله),
he is the only one who had a different view.
He told Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه, he said;
What will your answer be to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ on the Day of Judgment when He asks you
about appointing Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه to lead us, when you know his harshness.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه that was his makeup that was his personality
he's a very strong man.
And he had this great presence and he demands respect and his physical stature was huge.
So that added to his presence.
Abu Musa Al-Ash'ari(أبوموسى ألأشعري) he once went knocking on the door of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه,
he knocks three times and Umar(عُمَر) did not answer back.
So Abu Musa(أبوموسى) left.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), he came out and said: Why did you leave?
Abu Musa(أبوموسى) said: Because I heard Rasool Allah ﷺ say that
if you ask for permission three times and you're not given it, then leave.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: You're gonna bring me another witness,
that Rasool Allah ﷺ said that.
Abu Musa Al-Ash'ari(أبوموسى ألأشعري) left and he went to a meeting of Al-Ansaar(اَلْاَنْصَار),
Abu Saeed Al-Khudri(أبوسعيدألخدري) who is narrating this story. He says:
When Abu Musa(أبوموسى) came in his face was yellow, the color of his face changed.
They said: What happened to you?
He said: Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said that I have to bring a witness
that Rasool Allah ﷺ said this.
Abu Saeed Al-Khudri(أبوسعيدألخدري) said: The youngest among us, will go with you as a witness.
The Ansaar(ألأنْصَار) their youngsters would study with Rasool Allah ﷺ, Hadith(حديث),
while some of the other Sahabah(صحابه) were busy with work.
They had stores they had farms, they had jobs
so they couldn't spend all of their time with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
But the youth because their families are taking care of them.
They could afford spending all of their time with Rasool Allah ﷺ,
or some of the other Sahabah(صحابه) who made the conscious decision to do so,
like Abu Hurairah رضي الله عنه, he paid the price for that. He said:
وكُنْتُ ألْزَمُ رَسولَ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللهُ عليه وسلَّمَ علَى مِلْءِ بَطْنِي،
He said: I would accompany Rasool Allah ﷺ on an empty stomach
because when Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره) in the later days would narrate all of these Ahadith(احاديث).
Some people started questioning Abu Hurairah(أبوهريرة)
and saying how come you know all of these Ahadith(احاديث)
while the Sahabah(صحابه), who became Muslim before you don't know all of this Ahadith(أحاديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Abu Hurairah(أبوهريرة) said: Because they had work to do, they had businesses, they had farms,
but I had nothing and I would accompany Rasool Allah ﷺ on an empty stomach
so one of the young Sahabah(صحابه) went and was witness for Abu Musa Al-Ash'ari(أبوموسى ألأشعري),
but the point to make is that that was the personality of Umar(عُمَر).
So Talha(طلحة) said that what will your response be to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ on the Day of Judgment.
Now Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said:
أجلِسُونِي
Because he was laying down, so he wanted them to make him sit, straight.
He said: Are you threatening me by Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.?
If Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ asks me: Why did I appoint Umar(عُمَر)?
I will say because he's the best among us.
Every person in his personality, there are things that you might dislike,
but Umar(عُمَر) is the best among you.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was, he took this comment seriously
because he reminded him by Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
So Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: This is, what I'll say.
And another narration,
"أمَّرتُ عليهم ألقويُّ الأمين"
If Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ asks me: Why do you appoint Umar(عُمَر) I will say
because he is Al-Qawwi(ألقوي), Al-Ameen(ألأمين) he is strong and the trustworthy.
And these were the two words that the daughter of the man in Mad'yan(مدين) used when she went to her father.
After Musa عليه السّلام provided their flock with water.
She went back to her father and said: O my father, why don't you hire that man?
Because the best man to hire is a man, who's strong and trustworthy
and that's how Musa(موسى) got a job in Mad'yan(مدين) and he lived there for 10 years.
So this woman or girl at the time, she was very young.
She was very wise in that statements.
So, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ mentions it in Qur'an
that these are the two requirements if you want to hire someone.
This is what you look for, in an interview when you want to hire somebody to work for you.
Is he strong? And strength here doesn't mean necessarily physical strength.
It means competency in that particular field.
So you're strong in the field.
You're competent in that particular field.
If it's a physically demanding work, then the person has to be physically fit.
If it's a mentally demanding work, then the person needs to be mentally fit and strong.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was the perfect person for this role.
He was very intelligent, very wise, very strong, very determined.
He had solid opinions, he can make decisions
and he demanded respect from the people around him.
And that's why Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said: I'm going to appoint him to lead you.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه called Abu Obaidah رضي الله عنه to write down
the appointment of Umar(عُمَر), so it was written down.
And then he had it announced in the Masjid(مسجد)
and then he had the people give Baiyah(بَيْعة) to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
while he was still alive.
So the Baiyah(بَيْعة) of Umar(عمر) did not happen, after the death of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
As soon as Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه died
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) immediately assumed his position as Khalifah(خليفه)
there was no Baiyah(بَيْعة) that happened after the death, it was already done
and completed before the death of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
The illness of Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) carried on, and his situation was getting worse,
until it was the 15th day.
So Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) asked his daughter Ayesha(عائشه), he said: What day did Rasool Allah ﷺ die?
She said: He died on a Monday, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: And this is Monday.
So I think that this will be my last day.
Now this is a very interesting statement.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was very keen on following Rasool Allah ﷺ
his whole Khilafah(خِلَافَه) is an example of followings Sunnah(سنة).
And not just following Sunnah(سنة) in things that don't cost you anything.
He was following Sunnah(سنة) on issues that could cost him and the entire community, their life.
The issue of sending out the army of Osama(أسامة) was not something to be taken light.
That was a very serious risk,
and then insisting on having Osama(أسامة) lead the army and
not appointing somebody older than him. He was only 18 years old.
And then the fact that he never changed the post of
anyone appointed by Rasool Allah ﷺ and make it clear,
إِنَّمَا أَنَا مُتَّبِعٌ وَلَسْتُ بِمُبْتَدِعٍ
That I am a man, who will follow and I'm not a man who will innovate.
I'm going to follow Rasool Allah ﷺ and I'm not going to come up with Bid'ah(بدعة).
He was very insistent, and persistent on following the Sunnah(سنة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ to the letter.
And it seems that he even wanted to follow the Sunnah(سنة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ in his death,
so he expected that he would die on the same day as Rasool Allah ﷺ died.
And it happened, he died on a Monday and Rasool Allah ﷺ died on a Monday
and Rasool Allah ﷺ died at the age of 63 and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) dies at the age of 63.
So he's following Rasool Allah ﷺ, in his life and in his death.
His last words, in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) were,
تَوَفَّنِي مُسْلِمًا وَأَلْحِقْنِي بِالصَّالِحِينَ
My Lord, take me as a Muslim and join me with the righteous,
take me as a Muslim and make me join the righteous, make me join my closest friend Muhammadﷺ,
and make me join the Sahabah رضي الله عنه who passed away before.
These were his last words, in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
He died the 21st of Jama Al-Aakhirah(جمادالآخِرة) the 13th year of Hijrah(هجرة).
So, his Khilafah(خِلَافَه) was two years, three months and 10 days that was it.
All of these events, battles, Da'wah(دعوة)
were done within two years, three months and 10 days.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه had the honor of leading the Salah(صلاة) of Janazah(جنازة) on Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
Now when I think about this, the Imam(اِمَام) of Salat-Ul-Janazah(صلاة الجنازة) makes Dua(دُعَا) for the person, who dies.
The Imam(اِمَام) makes a Dua(دُعَا) and everybody behind the Imam(اِمَام) is also making Dua(دُعَا) for the deceased.
So you can imagine Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه covered in the Thaub(ثوب), the cloth, the white cloth,
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) is the one leading the Salah(صلاة) on him
and he is one making Dua(دُعَا) for Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه, it's Umar(عُمَر)
making Dua(دُعَا) for his close friend Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
asking Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ to grant him the highest level in Jannah(جنة).
And then Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) and Uthman Ibn Affan رضي الله عنه
and Talha Bin Obaidellah(طلحة بن عبيدالله) and Abdur Rahman Ibn Abi Bakr(عبدالرحمن إبن أبي بكر)
were the ones, who would lower the body of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه in his grave.
The grave of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه would be in the room of his daughter Ayesha(عائشه)
right next to the grave of Muhammadﷺ.
And out of respect for Muhammadﷺ, the head of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
was placed at the same level as the shoulders of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So he's not put right next to him, but he's a little bit behind.
Abdullah Bin Umar(عبدالله بن عمر) he says I came rushing I wanted to enter into the grave and lower the body.
But I came after the body was already lowered and my father told me it's already done.
But the ones, who did that were Umar(عُمَر), Uthman(عثمان), Talha(طلحة)
and Abdur Rahman Ibn Abi Bakr رضي الله عنهم أجمعين
After two years, three months and 10 days Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه succeeded in.
Number one, establishing the rules of Khilafah(خِلَافَه) in Islam.
Number two, starting the mission of carrying out the Da'wah(دعوة) to the entire world
because during the time of Muhammadﷺ, the Da'wah(دعوة) was still within the peninsula.
And the only exception to that was Mu'tah(مَؤتَة) and Tabook(تبوك).
But even with Mu'tah(مَؤتَة) and Tabook(تبوك), even though they were within Roman territory,
but it was still populated by Arab tribes in these southern parts of Ash-Sham(ألشَّام),
but it was Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه, who started the mission of Da'wah(دعوة),
into the different nations of the world, the Persian people, the Roman people and beyond.
So he was the teacher and the guide of the Mujahideen(مجاهدين) and the Duaah(دعاة) both.
He never had allowed himself the luxury of having spare time.
He never allowed himself the luxury of relaxing
and he never allowed himself to benefit financially from his post.
We did talk earlier about the demands of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) in his salary and even the bargaining.
When he said that this is not enough.
But he was doing it because he had a certain standard of living that he has to take care of himself and his family.
In addition to that he was very generous.
Before he died, since he still had some wealth leftover from his business days,
before Khilafah(خِلَافَه) he had pieces of land.
He told his daughter Ayesha(عائشه), I want you to sell my property
and then to pay back to the Muslim treasury.
All of the money that I took as a salary when I was Khalifah(خليفه).
I have the money, give it back to the Muslim Treasury.
When Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) heard about that, he said;
رحم الله أبا بكر، لقد أتعب من بعده
May Allah have mercy on Abu Bakr(ابوبكر),
he's making a difficult on the ones, who will come after him.
He's setting a standard that is too high, he's going to make it difficult on us.
You return all of the money that you have taken from the treasury
even though it was Halal(حلال) for you.
You deserve, it was not a deserve, it was less than what he deserves.
He got the money because he had to support a family.
And now since he has money left over, he's gonna pay it back to the Treasury.
So all of what was taken by Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was returned to Bait-Al-Maal-Al-Muslimeen(بيت المال المسلمين).
صَّلَواةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِ ألأولين والآخرين محمد إبن عبدالله وَعلى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
سبحانك اللهم وبحمدك نشهد و الله إله إلَّا أنت نستغفرك ونتوب عليك